Guide to the Nellie Beatrice Osborn Allen papers, 1916-1946.
Allen, Nellie Beatrice Osborn papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Nellie Beatrice Osborn Allen papers, 1916-1946.
6338
Allen, Nellie Beatrice Osborn,
1.5 cubic feet, 6 Mapcase Folders.
Photographs and architectural plans.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Photographs, planting plans, drawings, and blueprints of gardens designed by Allen while a student at the Lowthorpe School and in her professional practice. Also an album of photographs of English gardens taken by Allen in 1938.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Born in Cameron, Missouri in 1869, little is known about Allen's early years, education, and marriage to Sidney P. Allen. She attended the Lowthorpe School of Landscape Architecture between 1916 and 1919 in Groton, Massachusetts, under the name Beatrice Osborn Allen. In 1921 she visited gardens in England and Italy, including Gertrude Jekyll’s Munstead Wood. Between 1921 and the late 1940s Allen maintained a landscape architectural practice based in New York City, designing residential gardens primarily in the New York and New England area under the name Nellie B. Allen. Like many graduates of the Lowthorpe program, Allen excelled in the design of Anglo-American-style perennial borders, such as those at Dellwood, the John Henry Hammond estate in Mount Kisco. Other projects include the Isabel Dodge Sloane estate on Long Island, Three Waters estate in Gloucester, Massachusetts, Thornedale in Millbrook, New York, and the Anne Morgan estate in Mount Kisco. She was also a consultant for the Bishop’s Garden at the National Cathedral in Washington, and designed a parterre garden in collaboration with Constance Boardman for the 1939 New York World’s Fair. Her gardens were occasionally featured in House Beautiful, Landscape Architecture, and Country Life in America, but none of her gardens survive. (Taken from The Cultural Landscape Foundation)
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Photographs, planting plans, drawings, and blueprints of gardens designed by Allen while a student at the Lowthorpe School and in her professional practice. Also an album of photographs of English gardens taken by Allen in 1938.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Allen, Nellie Beatrice Osborn, 1869-1961.; Lowthorpe School.
Subjects:
Women landscape architects.; Landscape architecture.; Flower gardening.; Gardens.; Knot gardens.; Garden borders.; Gardens, English.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Architectural drawings.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Photographs
  - Mrs. James B. Clemens, New York, NY (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clifford McCall, East Hampton, NY (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Dellwood" - J.H. Hammond, Mt. Kisco, NY (Box 1, Folder 3a-3j)
  - Frank Bliss, New Rochelle, NY (Box 1, Folder 4a-4g)
  - Edwin Cole, Westport Harbor, NY (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Judge J. Harry Covington, Washington D.C. (Box 1, Folder 6a-6c)
  - "Otahnagon" Anne Morgan and Anne Vanderbilt, Mt. Kisco, NY (Box 1, Folder 7a-7b)
  - "Three Waters" Edith Notman, Gloucester, MA (Box 1, Folder 8a-8f)
  - Frank Bliss (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Brookmeade" - Sloane (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. James B. Clemens (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Judge J. Harry Covington (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Dellwood" - J.H. Hammond (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lowthorpe (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clifford McCall (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Otahnagon" Anne Morgan and Anne Vanderbilt (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "Thorndale" N.B. Allen (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Three Waters" Edith Notman (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photograph of Nellie B. Allen (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - English Lavender and Yew (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Buttress Yew Border at New Place (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Testaceum Lilies and Gypsophila (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mrs. W.D. Miller (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Photograph Album of English Gardens, 1938 (Box 2)
- Plans
  - Lowthorpe School drawings (5), 1917-1919 (Folder 1)
  - Garden plan for Mrs. Charles A. Morss, Chestnut Hill, MA, April 1919 (Folder 1)
    Possibly an assignment from the Lowthrope School
  - Cedar Acres, Belmont MA, May 1919 (Folder 1)
    Road Construction Plan
  - Mrs. Jecyll's Blue, Gold, Green, Grey, and Orange Garden plans, Undated (Folder 1)
  - Herb Garden (with list of plants), Undated (Folder 1)
  - Informal Knot Garden, Undated (Folder 1)
  - Sketch for the Garden of Mr. J.M. Tate Jr., Sewickley, PA, May 23, 1929 (Folder 1)
  - Leon M. Gecker, Crafts NY, November 23, 1945 (Folder 1)
    Planting Plan with topographical survey
    Planting Plan for Perennial and Annual Flower Garden Terrace (blueprint and plan on tracing paper)
  - Border of Sweet-Leaved Geraniums, March 10, 1942 (Folder 1)
  - Plan entitled "In Springtime the Sweet-Leaved Geraniums is planted with Choice May-Flowering Tulips", Undated (Folder 1)
  - Plan entitled "Lupins Against a Strong Background" (Folder 1)
  - Wave Hill Rock Garden (Folder 2)
    Mylar tracings of original blueprints (c. 1934) at Wave Hill
  - Morgan-Vanderbilt Estate, Mt. Kisco, NY, c. 1931 (Folder 3-5)
  - Lowthrorpe School Exercises, c. 1917 (Folder 6)